<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- <?xml:stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://db.systemsbiology.net/devPM/sbeams/doc/Microarray/Affy_help/Affy_help.xslt"?> --> 
	<help_document type="Download Affy Data">
	<overview>
	Many Affy files can be downloaded or viewed directly from SBEAMS		
	</overview>
	<all_summaries>
		<summary>
			<name>Access the Download Page</name>
		
			<description>To download or view Affy files from a particular project 
				go to the ProjectHome page. </description>
				<all_steps>
					<step>Select the project from the drop down located at the top of the page.</step>
					<step>Click the tab "Data Download" near the top of the page</step>
					<step>To download files: Select the arrays to retrieve information from.  The default is to download all the CEL files from a project</step>
					<step>The check boxes located under the Affy Tab will select or de-select all the files with that particular extension</step>
					<step>Once all the files are selected click the button "Get_affy_array_files"</step>
					<step>Select a location to save the zip file containing all the information selected for downloading</step>
					</all_steps>
			
			<extra_data data_type="link">
				<description>Open Link</description>
				<link_info type="sbeams_page" href="cgi/Microarray/main.cgi?tab=data_download">ProjectHome Page</link_info>
			</extra_data>
		
		</summary>
		<summary>
			<name>File Types</name>
		<description>Here is a brief description of all the file types available for viewing or downloading from SBEAMS</description>
			<table_info>
			  <section name="File Extension">
			    <entry>CHP</entry>
			    <entry>CEL</entry>
			    <entry>XML</entry>
				<entry>RPT</entry>
				<entry>R_CHP</entry>
				<entry>JPEG</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_PF.jpg</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_T.jpg</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_F.jpg</entry>
			  </section>
			  <section name="Description">
			   <entry>CHP. Binary Affymetrix file. CHP files contain probe set analysis results generated from Affymetrix software.</entry>
			    <entry>CEL. Binary Affymetrix file. The CEL file stores the results of the intensity calculations on the pixel values of the DAT file</entry>
			    <entry>XML. MAGE XML Affymetrix file.  Contains information from Affymetrix GCOS Software collected during sample preparation, hybridization, washing and scanning.</entry>
				<entry>RPT. Text report.  Contains information about the CHP file, used for basic quality control</entry>
				<entry>R_CHP. Text File.  Contains Probe set intensity values, calculated by using R/Bioconductor affy mas5.0 algorithms</entry>
				<entry>JPEG. Jpeg image of the Affy Chip generated by R using the image method within the affy library</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_PF.jpg.  Electrophoregram image of the Pre-fragmented cRNA</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_T.jpg.  Electrophoregram image of the total RNA</entry>
				<entry>EGRAM_F.jpg.  Electrophoregram image of the fragmented cRNA</entry>
			  </section>
			<section name="View File Directly">
			    <entry>NO</entry>
			    <entry>NO</entry>
			    <entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>No</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
			  </section>  
			<section name="Download">
			   <entry>Yes</entry>
			    <entry>Yes</entry>
			    <entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
				<entry>Yes</entry>
			  </section>
			</table_info>	
			
	
		</summary>
		
	</all_summaries>
	
	
</help_document>