<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<SBEAMS_EXPORT>
    <PR_instrument_type
        instrument_type_description="Electrospray Ionization Ion Trap Mass spectrometer"
        record_status="N"
        created_by_id="3"
        sort_order="100"
        instrument_type_name="ESI-ITMS"
        date_modified="2002-08-16 13:57:40"
        date_created="2002-07-04 16:49:53"
        instrument_type_id="1"
        owner_group_id="1"
        modified_by_id="3" />
    <PR_instrument
        record_status="N"
        created_by_id="3"
        sort_order="60"
        date_modified="2002-08-16 14:13:19"
        date_created="2002-08-16 14:13:19"
        instrument_type_id="1"
        instrument_description="HP1100LC/Dionix autosampler coupled to LCQ DECA"
        instrument_id="2"
        comment="This is the first ion trap purchased for the high throughput core
proteomics facility. Unlike the 'classic' ion trap, it is capable of up to
ten levels of tandem mass spectrometry (MSMS), though it typically only
runs at the first level for proteomics research. It is coupled to the
Hewlett Packard (now Agilent Technologies) HP1100 HPLC system through a
Cytopeia/Mass Evolution electrospray source. Samples are typically loaded
via the Dionix/LC Packings FAMOS autosampler onto hand made trap columns
incorporating C18 reverse phase silica beads and New Objective pre-made
frits. The sample is typically desalted with 20 ul buffer A, then pushed
onto a hand made 75 um x 10 cm C18 reverse phase tip integrated columns
through differential valve switching coupled to Upchurch fingertight
fittings. Electrospray charging is through platinum wire incorporated in
the Upchurch fingertight fittings. This is a single user platform machine,
wherein both quantitative and qualitative proteomics multi-sample and/or
multi-run experiments are performed on samples submitted to the core
facility. Data is typically collected in centroid form, converted to ICIS
format, and searched using the SEQUEST algorithm."
        owner_group_id="1"
        modified_by_id="3"
        instrument_name="LCQ DECA" />
</SBEAMS_EXPORT>
